Guide to the William Graham Sumner Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- Writings, 1859-1940; Series II; 43' plus 32 drawers of notecards (77 boxes and 1 folio)
  - Subject Files
    - F. A. Walker, undated (Box 89, Folder 1914)
    - "Wheat Corner", undated (Box 89, Folder 1915)
    - "Pali Life of Christ", undated (Box 89, Folder 1916)
    - "Corners Illegal", undated (Box 89, Folder 1917)
    - "Prohibition", undated (Box 89, Folder 1918)
    - "St. Peter, Gospel of", undated (Box 89, Folder 1919)
    - "Passes Railroads", undated (Box 89, Folder 1920)
    - "Suez", undated (Box 89, Folder 1921)
    - "Whooping Cough", undated (Box 89, Folder 1922)
    - "Pensions", undated (Box 89, Folder 1923)
    - "Politics", undated (Box 89, Folder 1924)
    - "Surplus", undated (Box 89, Folder 1925)
    - "Strikes", undated (Box 89, Folder 1926)
    - "Tariff", undated (Box 89, Folder 1927)
    - "Flour", undated (Box 89, Folder 1928)
    - "France List of Ministries '79-'92", undated (Box 89, Folder 1929)
    - "Repudiation", undated (Box 89, Folder 1930)
    - "Silver in Sandwich Islands", undated (Box 89, Folder 1931)
    - "Boycotting", undated (Box 89, Folder 1932)
    - "Germany", undated (Box 89, Folder 1933)
    - "Banks", undated (Box 89, Folder 1934)
    - "Debts, Public", undated (Box 89, Folder 1935)
    - "Minneapolis", undated (Box 89, Folder 1936)
    - "Street Cleaning", undated (Box 89, Folder 1937)
    - "Platforms", undated (Box 89, Folder 1938)
    - "The Confederacy - South", undated (Box 89, Folder 1939)
    - "Exports American Manufacturers", undated (Box 89, Folder 1940)
    - "Oleomargarine", undated (Box 89, Folder 1941)
    - "Wages", undated (Box 89, Folder 1942)
    - "Education", undated (Box 89, Folder 1943)
    - "The Sun ", undated (Box 89, Folder 1944)
    - "Miss McCrea", undated (Box 89, Folder 1945)
    - "Coal Strike", undated (Box 89, Folder 1946)
    - "Southern Feeling", undated (Box 89, Folder 1947)
    - "Lord A. Campbell", undated (Box 89, Folder 1948)
    - "President U.S. Visits to Congress", undated (Box 89, Folder 1949)
    - "Autocopyist", undated (Box 89, Folder 1950)
    - "Puritan", undated (Box 89, Folder 1951)
    - "Paternalism", undated (Box 89, Folder 1952)
    - "Railroad rates and other securities", undated (Box 89, Folder 1953)
    - "Military System of France, Origin of", undated (Box 89, Folder 1954)
    - "Vermont Land", undated (Box 89, Folder 1955)
    - "Meteoric Diamonds", undated (Box 89, Folder 1956)
    - "Patents", undated (Box 89, Folder 1957)
    - "American Exports", undated (Box 89, Folder 1958)
    - "Walras", undated (Box 89, Folder 1959)
    - "Bourbons", undated (Box 90, Folder 1960)
    - "The Cheque Bank", undated (Box 90, Folder 1961)
    - "New Zealand Labor", undated (Box 90, Folder 1962)
    - "Nail Holes Inscription Read By", undated (Box 90, Folder 1963)
    - "Mountain Formation", undated (Box 90, Folder 1964)
    - "Wool Duties", undated (Box 90, Folder 1965)
    - "Ice Caves", undated (Box 90, Folder 1966)
    - "Philanthropy", undated (Box 90, Folder 1967)
    - "The Exchanges", undated (Box 90, Folder 1968)
    - "Bounty", undated (Box 90, Folder 1969)
    - "Tolstoi", undated (Box 90, Folder 1970)
    - "Pauperism", undated (Box 90, Folder 1971)
    - "South Carolina", undated (Box 90, Folder 1971)
    - "Industrial Schools", undated (Box 90, Folder 1971)
    - "Water", undated (Box 90, Folder 1972)
    - "Polenba", undated (Box 90, Folder 1972)
    - "Shorthand machine", undated (Box 90, Folder 1973)
    - "Mars", undated (Box 90, Folder 1974)
    - "Mormon Massacre", undated (Box 90, Folder 1975)
    - "China", undated (Box 90, Folder 1976)
    - "Tortillas", undated (Box 90, Folder 1976)
    - "Banks in Scandinavia", undated (Box 90, Folder 1977)
    - "Bank notes", undated (Box 90, Folder 1978)
    - "Financial Science", undated (Box 90, Folder 1979)
    - "Patrick Henry", undated (Box 90, Folder 1980)
    - "Photographic curiosity", undated (Box 90, Folder 1981)
    - "Franklin", undated (Box 90, Folder 1982)
    - "Germanicus", undated (Box 90, Folder 1983)
    - "Public frauds", undated (Box 90, Folder 1984)
    - "Freedman's Bank", undated (Box 90, Folder 1985)
    - Catholics and Schools, undated (Box 90, Folder 1986)
    - "Finances Russia", undated (Box 90, Folder 1987)
    - "Methuen Treaty", undated (Box 90, Folder 1988)
    - "Post Office", undated (Box 90, Folder 1989)
    - "Revolution", undated (Box 90, Folder 1990)
    - "French Politics and Finance", undated (Box 90, Folder 1990)
    - "Centenarians", undated (Box 90, Folder 1990)
    - "Railroad - A Queer", undated (Box 90, Folder 1991)
    - "Weights and measures", undated (Box 90, Folder 1992)
    - "Tobacco Grown in England and Ireland", undated (Box 90, Folder 1993)
    - "Previous question", undated (Box 90, Folder 1994)
    - "Rights of Man by Courcelle-Seneuil", undated (Box 90, Folder 1995)
    - "Woolen", undated (Box 90, Folder 1996)
    - "Reform of Parliament in England", undated (Box 90, Folder 1997)
    - "Public Debt - National and Municipal", undated (Box 90, Folder 1998)
    - "Strike. Germany", undated (Box 90, Folder 1999)
    - "Paupers", undated (Box 90, Folder 2000)
    - "Transportation", undated (Box 90, Folder 2001)
    - "Wheat", undated (Box 90, Folder 2002)
    - "Reciprocity", undated (Box 90, Folder 2003)
    - "Resumption", undated (Box 90, Folder 2004)
    - "Evolution", undated (Box 90, Folder 2005)
    - "Constitutional Law", undated (Box 90, Folder 2006)
    - "Coinage, England", undated (Box 90, Folder 2007)
    - "Chicago Land Values", undated (Box 90, Folder 2008)
    - "Cuba", undated (Box 90, Folder 2009)
    - "National Finances", undated (Box 90, Folder 2010)
    - "Sugar", undated (Box 90, Folder 2011)
    - "Engadine Newspapers", undated (Box 90, Folder 2012)
    - "Thread", undated (Box 90, Folder 2013)
  - Miscellaneous Writings
    - "Fernando the Chieftan of Northern Corsica. A Tale by William G. Sumner.", 1851 November 5 (Box 91, Folder 2014)
    - "The College Scrape. A Farce in One Act", 1858 December 30 (Box 91, Folder 2015)
    - "Adventure at the Convent of the Great Saint Bernard", 1858 April 27 (Box 91, Folder 2016)
    - "The Grave in the Woods", 1859 March 21 (Box 91, Folder 2017)
    - "Subjects for Theses and Compositions", 1886 (Box 91, Folder 2018)
    - A Piece of Fiction about the Future, 1880-1889 (?) (Box 91, Folder 2019)
    - "Outline of a Proposed Curriculum", 1897 (?) (Box 91, Folder 2020)
    - Proposal to write a book to be entitled The Dollar, 1899 (?) (Box 91, Folder 2021)
    - "The Phantom Locomotive", undated (Box 91, Folder 2022)
    - "An Indian's Revenge", undated (Box 91, Folder 2023)
    - "Theme", undated (Box 91, Folder 2024)
    - Genealogy of French Kings; Genealogy of the Kings of England and the Royal Family of England, undated (Box 91, Folder 2025)
    - Notes taken from Sumner's copy of The Financier and the Finances of the American Revolution, undated (Box 91, Folder 2026)
    - Scattered notes, undated (Box 91, Folder 2026a)
    - Notes and newspaper clippings on the coal industry, undated (Box 91, Folder 2027)
    - Fiction: no title, undated (Box 92, Folder 2028)
    - Scandinavian grammar, undated (Box 92, Folder 2029)
    - Notes on United States economic history, undated (Box 92, Folder 2030)
    - Committee Report on the Biology Dept. - by W. G. Sumner, undated (Box 92, Folder 2031)
    - Sumner's outline for Science and Society, undated (Box 92, Folder 2032)
    - Sumner's outline for Science and Society, undated (Box 92, Folder 2033)
    - Sumner's outline for Science and Society, undated (Box 92, Folder 2034)
    - Outline for Societology, undated (Box 92, Folder 2035)
    - Chronology of World History, undated (Box 92, Folder 2036)
    - "On the Concentration of Wealth" (TMs), undated (Box 92, Folder 2037)
    - "Memorandum suggested by a Study of the Digest of Opinions Expressed at the Meeting of the Academical Professors", 1899 November 28 (Box 93, Folder 2038)
    - A proposed college curriculum, undated (Box 93, Folder 2039)
    - Report of Committee on Senior Law courses, 1900 March 22 (Box 93, Folder 2039)
    - Report of the Committee to suggest a possible alternative for the entrance requirement in Greek, 1901 (Box 93, Folder 2040)
    - Essay: On Sumner's Thought (TMs), undated (Box 93, Folder 2041)
    - Essay: "William Graham Sumner and the World Frontier Thesis" (TMs), undated (Box 93, Folder 2042)
    - Material contributed to the Living Church, 1869-1871 (?) (Box 93, Folder 2043)
    - Material contributed to the Living Church, 1869-1871 (?) (Box 93, Folder 2044)
    - Play: "The Belle of New Haven" Act I only, undated (Box 93, Folder 2045)
    - Diary of Eliot Sumner, n.y. July 26-August 21 (Box 93, Folder 2046)
    - Eyesight test results for Webster School, New Haven, undated (Box 93, Folder 2047)
    - Eyesight test results for Oak Street School, New Haven, undated (Box 93, Folder 2048)
    - Eyesight test results for Davenport School, New Haven, undated (Box 93, Folder 2049)
    - Eyesight test results for Eaton School, New Haven, undated (Box 93, Folder 2050)
    - Eyesight test results for Dwight School, New Haven, undated (Box 93, Folder 2051)
    - Eyesight test results for Hillhouse High School, New Haven, undated (Box 93, Folder 2052)
  - Notecards, Booklists, and Indexes
    Separated Materials
    A file cabinet containing 32 drawers of 5" x 8" notecards (approximately 250,000) used in the preparation of Science of Society was transferred to Human Relations Area Files (HRAF), in 1998.
    - Booklist: Sociology, undated (Box 94, Folder 2053)
    - Booklist: Sociology, undated (Box 95, Folder 2054)
    - Booklist: Catalogue of books in the Library of William G. Sumner Vol. I, undated (Box 96, Folder 2055)
    - Booklist: Catalogue of books in the Library of William G. Sumner Vol. II, undated (Box 97, Folder 2056)
    - Booklist: Sociology, undated (Box 98, Folder 2057)
    - Booklist: Sociology, undated (Box 99, Folder 2058)
    - Folkways
      - Index: A, undated (Box 100, Folder 2059)
      - Index: B, undated (Box 100, Folder 2060)
      - Index: C, undated (Box 100, Folder 2061)
      - Index: D, undated (Box 100, Folder 2062)
      - Index: E, undated (Box 100, Folder 2063)
      - Index: F, undated (Box 100, Folder 2064)
      - Index: G, undated (Box 100, Folder 2065)
      - Index: H, undated (Box 100, Folder 2066)
      - Index: I, undated (Box 100, Folder 2067)
      - Index: J - L, undated (Box 100, Folder 2068)
      - Index: M -, undated (Box 100, Folder 2069)
      - Index: N - O, undated (Box 100, Folder 2070)
      - Index: P, undated (Box 100, Folder 2071)
      - Index: Q - R, undated (Box 100, Folder 2072)
      - Index: S, undated (Box 100, Folder 2073)
      - Index: T - V, undated (Box 100, Folder 2074)
      - Index: W - Z, undated (Box 100, Folder 2075)
      - Index, undated (Box 101, Folder 2076-2083)
    - Historical notes on the American Revolution, undated (Box 102, Folder 2084)
    - Note guides for Money I, Money II, Industrial Revolution, Renaissance, and Middle Ages, undated (Box 103, Folder 2085)
    - Note guides to "Manors" and "Current Lectures - Banking", undated (Box 104, Folder 2086)
    - Bibliographical notes, undated (Box 105, Folder 2087)
    - Bibliographical notes, undated (Box 106, Folder 2088)
    - Notecards: "Money I", undated (Box 107, Folder 2089)
    - Notecards: "Money II", undated (Box 108, Folder 2090)
    - Notecards: "Middle Ages, Manors, Law, State", undated (Box 109, Folder 2091)
    - Notecards: "Middle Ages, Notes on Renaissance, Commerce and Financial Cities", undated (Box 110, Folder 2092)
    - Notecards: "Middle Ages, Notes on Renaissance, Crusades", undated (Box 111, Folder 2093)
    - Notecards: "Industrial Revolution", undated (Box 112, Folder 2094)
    - Unidentified index and booklists, undated (Box 112, Folder 2094)
- Memorabilia, 1847-1912; Series III; 4' (9 boxes and 2 folios)
  Series III has four catagories or sections: Scrapbooks, Printed Material, Photographs, and Financial Records. Each section is arranged chronologically.
  Two additional Sumner scrapbooks are available on Hist. MSS Film 71.
  - Scrapbooks
    - Yale scrapbook #1, 1873-1894 (Box 113, Folder 2095)
    - Yale scrapbook #2, 1896-1897 (Box 114, Folder 2096)
    - Yale scrapbook #3, 1898-1901 (Box 115, Folder 2097)
    - Obituaries: William Graham Sumner, 1910 (Box 116, Folder 2098)
  - Printed Material
    - Term examination in Money, undated (Box 117, Folder 2099)
    - Term examinations in Banking, undated (Box 117, Folder 2100)
    - Term examinations in Taussig, undated (Box 117, Folder 2101)
    - Term examinations in International Trade, Finance, Tariff History, and Public Debts, undated (Box 117, Folder 2102)
    - Term examinations in Science of Society, undated (Box 117, Folder 2103)
    - William G. Sumner's first book Self-Dependence or "I'll Not Do So Again", 1847 (Box 118, Folder 2104)
    - Course catalogue for George-Augustus University of Gottingen, 1855 (Box 118, Folder 2105)
    - William G. Sumner's Bible, 1856 (Box 118, Folder 2106)
    - Academic record of William G. Sumner and student manual from George-Augustus University in Göttingen, 1864 (Box 118, Folder 2107)
    - Oxford Undergraduate's Journal, 1866 May 30 (Box 118, Folder 2108)
    - "The Story of Father's Burial for My Mother and Sisters" Frederic B. Elliott, 1868 September 6 (Box 118, Folder 2109)
    - Certificates, undated (Box 118, Folder 2110)
    - Certificates, 1869, 1872, 1931, undated (Box 118, Folder 2111)
    - Obituaries and tributes to Edward A. Washburn, 1881 (Box 118, Folder 2112)
    - Review of Sumner's "What the Social Classes Owe Each Other", 1883 November 15 (Box 118, Folder 2113)
    - Yale memorabilia, 1860-1942 (Box 118, Folder 2114)
    - Note on the John Eliot Memorial Window, 1894 (Box 118, Folder 2115)
    - Reunion dinner program for alumni of George-Augustus University of Göttingen, 1898 (Box 118, Folder 2116)
    - Obituaries and tributes to Alfred P. Rockwell, 1904 January (Box 118, Folder 2117)
    - Copyright for Sumner's Folkways, 1906 September 4 (Box 118, Folder 2118)
    - International Free Trade Congress, 1908 (Box 118, Folder 2119)
    - Jeannie Sumner's notes on William G. Sumner's funeral, 1910 (Box 118, Folder 2120)
    - Newspapers and magazine tributes to Sumner, 1910 (Box 118, Folder 2121)
    - Tribute to Sumner, Yale Courant, 1912 April (Box 118, Folder 2122)
    - 18 types of investment securities compiled by William G. Sumner, undated (Box 119, Folder 2123)
    - Chart of colonial taxation 1754-1765 (Box 119, Folder 2124)
    - Examinations pasted over pages of Index on Banking in the United States, undated (Box 119, Folder 2124)
    - 7 graphs on United States banking, currency and trade 1780-1872, undated (Box 119, Folder 2125)
    - 8 charts of horses and skulls 1 wall table of chart entitled "Anthropology" (Box 119, Folder 2126)
    - 1 chart entitled "Societal System" 1 cardboard chart of mathematical formulas, undated (Box 119, Folder 2126)
    - Miscellaneous mimeographed material, undated (Box 119, Folder 2127)
    - Miscellaneous newspaper and magazine clippings, undated (Box 119, Folder 2128)
    - Miscellaneous printed material, undated (Box 119, Folder 2129-1230)
    - 2 ship logs: To Italy; To England, n.y. May 27, n.y. September 22 (Box 119, Folder 2131)
    - Certificate by Jeannie Sumner authorizing a Spanish translation of "What the Social Classes Owe Each Other", undated (Box 119, Folder 2132)
    - Sample of Thomas Sumner's hair, undated (Box 119, Folder 2133)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 119, Folder 2134)
    - Book reviews and miscellaneous notes, undated (Box 119, Folder 2135)
  - Photos
    - Photograph: Phillips Brooks, 1891 December 12 (Box 120, Folder 2136)
    - W.G. Sumner as a young man, undated (Box 120, Folder 2136a)
    - Photographs: William Graham Sumner, 1873(?), 1895, 1902, 1907-1908 (Box 120, Folder 2137-2142)
    - Photographs: William Graham Sumner, undated (Box 120, Folder 2143)
    - Photographs: William Graham Sumner, undated (Box 120, Folder 2144-2145)
    - Portrait: William G. Sumner by Dean Keller, 1940 (Box 120, Folder 2146)
    - Photograph: unidentified woman [transferred to Historical Picture Collection, box A14 item A169], unidentified man, undated (Box 120, Folder 2147)
    - Photograph: [Christening of Alfred Rockwell Sumner?], 1909 (Box 120, Folder 2147a)
    - Photograph: Diana Rockwell, wife of Eliot Sumner, and her mother, Circa1900 (Box 120, Folder 2147b)
    - Photographs and negatives: Tap Day, unidentified, 1906 (Box 120, Folder 2147c)
  - Financial Records
    - Living Church accounts, 1869-1870 (Box 121, Folder 2148)
    - Checks from William G. Sumner, 1871-1879, 1887, 1900 (Box 121, Folder 2149)
    - Receipts, 1871, 1876, 1877, 1888-1890, 1899-1904, 1906-1908, undated (Box 121, Folder 2150)
    - Probate documents of Elmira Elliott, 1876 (Box 121, Folder 2151)
    - Checks to William Graham Sumner, 1893-1896, 1904, 1906, 1909 (Box 121, Folder 2152)
    - Miscellaneous financial records, 1897, 1906, undated (Box 121, Folder 2153)
    - Contract and copyright statement 15 royalty statements: Ginn and Company, 1906 March 31 - 1917 February 1 (Box 121, Folder 2154)
    - 14 royalty statements: Houghton, Mifflin and Co., 1908 July 31 -1917 January 31 (Box 121, Folder 2155)
    - 16 royalty statements: Harper and Brothers, 1909 June 30 -1916 June 30 (Box 121, Folder 2156)
    - 16 royalty statements: Henry Holt and Co., 1910 April 25 - 1917 April 25 (Box 121, Folder 2157)
    - Commission statements. - Charles W. Scranton Co., 1913 February 5 - 1914 April 15 (Box 121, Folder 2158)
    - 8 royalty statements: Yale University Press, 1914 August 28 - 1917 February 27 (Box 121, Folder 2159)
    - Financial records from Henry Sumner, undated (Box 121, Folder 2160)
- Folios
  - Essays
    - "Laissez-Faire" (TMs), 1885-1889 (Box 122)
    - "Free Trade" (TMs), 1889 (Box 122)
    - "The Mediaeval Doctrine About Commerce" (TMs), 1889 (Box 122)
    - "Democratization of Industry" (TMs), undated (Box 122)
    - "Free Trade" (TMs), undated (Box 122)
    - "We Think" (TMs), undated (Box 122)
  - Memorabilia
    - 18 types of investment securities, compiled by W. G. Sumner for use in Yale University, 1890 (Box 122)
    - Unidentified index and booklists, undated (Box 123)
    - Chart of colonial taxation 1754-1765, undated (Box 123)
    - Examinations pasted over pages of Index on Banking in the United States, undated (Box 123)
    - Certificates, 1859-1909 (Box 124)
    - 7 graphs on United States banking, currency, and trade 1780-1872, undated (Box 124)
    - 8 charts of horses and skulls, undated (Box 124)
    - Wall table of chart entitled "Anthropology", undated (Box 124)
    - Chart entitled "Societal System", undated (Box 124)
    - Cardboard chart of mathematical formulas, undated (Box 124)
- Additional Material, 1863-1946; Accession 1989-M-035; 0.25; (1 box)
  Addition Inventory by Carol King 1988 Oct
  Received from: Watkinson Library, Trinity College, 1988 Jul 1
  - CORRESPONDENCE
    - Benson, Lawrence Slater, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Blagden, Silliman, 1889 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Butler, I.W., 1886 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Chapman, Kittie, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Conway, [?] D., 1892 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Ferguson, R., 1883 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Ford, Paul Leicester, 1891 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Godland, B., 1885 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Henderson, Isaac, 1909 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Henry, Sylvanus, 1890 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Husband, Mary Morris, 1863, 1893 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Keefe, A., 1896 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Kellog, D., Jr., undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Phelps, William Lyon, 1908 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Porter, Edwin L., 1887 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Sheldon, C., 1899 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Silver, W. E., 1899 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Slingluff, Fielder C., 1892-1893 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Tyler, Mason, 1885 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Wakeley, Ebenezer, 1896 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Williams, M. T., 1885 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Unidentified correspondence, 1887, undated (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - WRITINGS BY SUMNER
    - Biographical statement, undated (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Proposed classification of the Social Sciences, 1907 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - MEMORABILIA
    - Programs, syllabus, book reviews, and articles relating to Sumner's work, 1863-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Miscellaneous notes, financial papers, etc., 1885, 1928, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Loose photographs of Sumner family tombstones, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Newspaper clippings, 1890-1898, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)